（雷影）どこを狙っているのだ！
Who are you aiming at?
速すぎて　攻撃が当たりません！
You're too fast for our attacks!
（雷影）
今一度言う。　俺は　雷遁使いだ。
I'll say it again.
I am a Lightning Style User.
体に　雷遁をまとうことで
肉体の限界を超えた速度と→
When I arm myself with
the Lightning Style,
my speed and defensive power exceed
the normal limits of my body.
防御力を備えている。
風遁で攻め立てる以外
俺を倒す手はない。
Unless you attack with
the Wind Style,
you will never be able
to take me down.
（テマリ）それが　当たらないから
苦労する…。
The trouble is,
we can't land a blow even with that!
いや　それなら…。
No, wait...
風遁班！　攻撃フォーメーション　Ｃだ！
Wind Style Unit!
Attack Formation C!
はっ！
行くぞ！
Right!
Here we go!
フン！　騙し討ちすればいいものを
攻撃宣言などしおって。
Humph! Instead of doing it quietly,
she announces how
they're going to attack.
集団風遁術！
Group Wind Style Jutsu!
風遁　掛け網！
Wind Style: Casting Net!
わしの速度を上回る広域術か。
A wide-range jutsu
to overtake my speed...
見事だ。
Splendid!
うわっ！
よし　一気にたたみかけるぞ！
All right! We'll surround him
all at once!
always chasing after your shadow
itsu made mo oikakete iru anata no zanzo wo
when you dream, your face looks like it did before
yume ni miru yokogao ha ano koro no mama de
you run into the tall grass and disappear
se no takai kusanami ni hashiri satte kieta
I push through the memories and follow you
omoidasu kioku wo kakewake atoo uboku ha
it's frustrating as I run out of breath and in the end I'm unable to reach you
modokashiku mo iki wo kirashite saigo ha todokazu ni
far away
tooku
how many years ago was it?
nannenmae no koto desho
I left my heart at that place
nidoto modorenai ano basho ni
where I can never return
oite kite shimatta boku no kokoro sa
if this is a dream, if I can't get it back
moshimo yume naraba tori modosenai no nara
then how can I tell you how I feel?
kono kimochi ha do shite utaereba ii no
I'm still chasing after the shadow from that day
imadani oikakete iru ano hi no zanzo wo
though I spend my days in sorrow
kanashimi ni ake kurenagara mo ima
I'll live on in this world without you
anata naki sekai de boku wa ikiru yo
Paradox
ハァ　ハァ…。
いくら攻撃しても
手ごたえがない。
No matter how many times
we attack, there's no effect!
ダメージを与えられていないぞ！
We haven't inflicted any damage!
《最速の　きりきり舞いの術を
連続で当てまくるしかない》
Our only choice is to batter him
with consecutive top-speed Blade Dance!
ドダイか？
Is that you, Dodai?
（ドダイ）はい。
Yes.
三代目　雷影様は
スピード　パワー以上に→
The Third Lord Raikage was a shinobi
blessed not only with
strength and speed,
その異常な打たれ強さに
優れた忍であった。
but also with extraordinary
physical resilience.
唯一　三代目に届く
風遁の遠距離攻撃も→
Even long-distance Wind Style attacks,
which should reach him,
決定打には欠ける。
do not affect him.
もっと強い風遁使いが必要だ。
We need an even more
powerful Wind Style User.
私も　結構な
風遁使いなんだけどね。
I'm a pretty good
Wind Style User myself.
どうやって死んだんだ？　こいつ。
So how did he actually die?
（ドダイ）仲間を逃がすため
１万の敵を相手に→
In order to save his comrades...
He used himself as a decoy
and faced 10,000 enemy troops alone.
たった一人で戦い
オトリとなられた。
仲間の逃げる時間を稼ぐため→
It's said he stood for three days
and three nights
三日三晩　倒れなかったと聞く。
in order to buy enough time to
let his comrades escape.
（カブト）あいつを口寄せする間→
I need this one to
buy me some time...
こいつに　時間稼ぎを
してもらわないとな。
while I finish summoning him.
こっちで操るか。
Guess I'll just have to take over.
正直　ここの連合で
私以上の風遁使いは…。
Honestly, among the Allied Forces,
there isn't a stronger
Wind Style User than me.
（ナルト）いる！
There is!
俺だ！
It's me!
《何だ！？　ナルトなのか！？
What?! Is that Naruto?!
What is he doing here?
なんで　こんなところに？》
《この感じ　風遁だな。
That feels like Wind Style!
Is it a new Rasengan?
螺旋丸の進化版か？
この術なら　当たればいける！》
With this jutsu,
it just might work if it hits!
ダメだ！　その程度では。
No! That's not good enough!
あの雷の衣で…。
わかってる→
Not with his Cloak of Lightning...
I know! Raikage are
always super fast!
雷影を名乗るおっさんたちが
速いってのは。
《あいつ　はなからこれを狙って》
That's what he was aiming for!
《ダメだ！》
《また　かわされた！》
It's no use!
He dodged it again!
《陽動かけなきゃ
やっぱり　当たりもしない》
We have to distract him,
or it won't hit him!
オッケー　返ってきたところを…。
Okay! When it comes back...
この距離なら…。
At this distance...
当たる！
It's gonna hit!
《なんて威力の風遁だ。
これなら…》
That Wind Style is strong!
This will work...
今のうちだ。　封印班急げ！
ハッ！
Now, Sealing Corps! Hurry!
Right!
よし！
（みんな）おぉっ。
All right!
な…　なに！？
W-What?!
三代目
やはり　あなたは恐ろしく強い。
Third Raikage...
You are so strong,
it's frightening...
《ウソだろ。
螺旋手裏剣が効いてねえ》
I don't believe it.
Rasen Shuriken didn't work?!
さっきから
雷影様の目つきが変わった。
The look in Lord Raikage's eyes
has changed...
すでに完全に操られている。
He's been completely taken over.
あれは！
That's...?!
みんな　雷影様から離れろ！
Everyone, get away from
the Third Raikage!
土遁使いの忍たちは
今すぐ壁の用意だ。
Earth Style Shinobi,
form a wall immediately!
みんな　つなげろ！
（みんな）おう！　土遁　万里土流壁。
Everyone, link up!
– Right!
– Earth Style: Great Mud Wall!
散れ！
Disperse!
来い　ナルト！
うわっ！
Come with me, Naruto!
イテッ。
熔遁　護謨壁！
Lava Style: Rubber Wall!
なんだ？
What the—?!
三代目最強忍術
地獄突き四本貫手だ。
That was the Third Raikage's
most lethal ninjutsu...
The Piercing Four-Fingered
Thrust of Hell!
指先に雷チャクラをためて突く。
He accumulates Lightning Chakra
in his fingertip and strikes...
もともと突き技は
雷遁と相性がいい。
This thrust technique complements
the Lightning Style.
《カカシ先生の雷切りや
サスケの千鳥に似てるな》
Just like Kakashi Sensei's Lightning Blade
and Sasuke's Chidori.
みんな
今のうちにできるだけ離れろ！
Everyone, get as far away
as possible, now!
いや　出てくるところが
わかっているなら→
No! If we know where he'll appear,
we should aim for that spot all together!
そこを１点集中で狙う。
皆　構えろ！
Everyone, stand by!
これまで速すぎて
当てられなかった→
It's payback time for all
the times we missed!
攻撃の分もお返しするぜ。
よせ！　雲の忍の言うことを聞け！
Stop! Listen to the Cloud Shinobi!
Get him!
クソッ。
Damn it!
バカどもが。
Fools!
ぐわぁっ！
三本貫手に変えられてたか。
He's switched to
the Three-Fingered Assault!
なんだってんだ　あの術。
むちゃくちゃ強え。
What kind of jutsu is it anyway?
たった１人で何十人も一瞬で。
It's way too powerful!
He took dozens down in
an instant, all by himself!
あの地獄突きは
指の数を減らしていくほど→
The fewer the fingers he uses,
the more focused the energy and
力が１点に集中していき
三代目最強の矛となる。
the more powerful the Thrusts of Hell!
It's the Third's Invincible Spear!
そして　どんな術にも耐える
強靭な肉体が最強の盾となる。
And he can handle it with
his impermeable body.
It's his ultimate shield!
人なのか？　あのオッサン。
Is that old man even human...?
生身で尾獣と
やり合うことのできた→
They say he is the only shinobi
to have ever been able
ただ１人の忍といわれている。
マジ…。
to go head to head with a Tailed Beast,
unarmored and unarmed!
No way!
《すげえんだな　雷影ってのも》
Raikage are amazing!
Huh?
どうした？
じゃあ　どういうことだってばよ？
What's the matter?
So what's up with that?
何がだ？
ほら　あの胸の傷跡。
With what?
Look at that...
The scar on his chest!
最強の盾になる体なら
どうやって付いたんだ？
If his body's the ultimate shield,
how'd he get that?
螺旋手裏剣でもビクともしねえのに。
He didn't even flinch against
my Rasen Shuriken!
あれか。
三代目はみんなを逃がし→
Oh, that...
Once, the Third Raikage helped everyone
get away from the Eight Tails
たった１人で八尾の暴走を
止められたことがあった。
by stopping its rampage
all by himself.
そんじゃあ　八尾がやったのか？
Then the Eight Tails hurt him?
あの傷については
一切語られていない。
He called that the most
shameful incident of his life.
生涯の恥だと
誰にも理由は言われなかった。
One that he never spoke about...
四代目も知らぬことだ。
Not even the Fourth Raikage knows.
半端な攻撃じゃ
傷つかねえことはわかった。
Okay, I get that ordinary attacks
won't hurt him.
もし八尾との戦いでついた傷なら
八尾の最強の術ってことか。
But if he got hurt fighting
the Eight Tails,
then the Eight Tails' strongest jutsu is...
《八尾といえば》
Speaking of the Eight Tails...!
尾獣玉だ！
Tailed Beast Bomb!
（マツリ）テマリさん　どうするんです？
What'll we do, Lady Temari?!
あのナルトさんでさえ
倒せなかった相手ですよ？
Even that hero, Naruto, couldn't
take him down...
（ユカタ）えっ　ナルトさん？
あの木ノ葉の英雄の？
Huh?! Naruto?
You mean the hero of
the Hidden Leaf?
どこ？　どこ？
どの人が　そうなの？
Where? Where?
Which one is he?
ユカタ！　何見てたのよ！
Where were you looking, Yukata?!
さっき　派手な風遁術
ぶっぱなした人がそうよ！
He's the one who just released
that flashy Wind Style Jutsu!
えっ？　だって　さっきの人は　まだ
私たちと歳も変わらないでしょ？
Huh?!
But that guy's about
the same age as us!
そうよ。　あの歳で
暁のペインを１人で倒したのよ。
Yes! At his age, he managed
to defeat Pain of the Akatsuki!
じゃあ　木ノ葉の英雄が
倒せなかった相手と→
So how can we beat an enemy that
even the hero of the Hidden Leaf can't?
どうやって戦うんです？
だから
それを今　考えてるところだろ！
That's what I'm trying to
figure out right now!
風遁の使えん
近距離タイプのお前ら２人は→
You two can't use
long-distance Wind Style!
危険だから　とっとと下がってろ！
（２人）は…　は～い！
So go away, it's dangerous!
– R-Right!
ハァ…。
《で　どうする…
ナルトの　あの螺旋丸ですら→
So what'll we do?
Even Naruto's Rasengan couldn't
inflict serious damage.
致命傷を与えられない雷影相手に
どう戦えばいい…。
How do we fight the Raikage?
クッ　撤退も考慮に…。
だが　１人でも　やっかいな影だ。
We have to consider retreating.
What a nuisance these Kage are...
even one who's by himself.
分断できてる今が最善と言える。
This is the ideal time since
they're separated.
私たちが　ここを撤退して
他の影と合流されたら→
If we retreat and allow him to join up
with the other Kage, it will get worse.
それこそ手がつけられなくなる。
どうする…　どうすれば…》
What to do? What to do?
な…　何なんだ？　この感じは。
また　ナルトの術か何かか？
W-What's this I'm feeling?
Is Naruto trying another jutsu
or something?
《あぁっ…
これは　八尾と同じ尾獣玉。
Th-This is the Tailed Beast Bomb...
The same as the Eight Tails'!
これほど重いチャクラ玉を
人型のままで…。
He's holding a mass of chakra
this heavy in his human form?!
そんなことが…》
Is this even possible?
クッ…　クッ…。
ん～っ！
ん～っ！！
（みんな）うわ～！
うわっ！
《できるはずがない…
やはりな…》
I figured it was impossible.
何だ　どうした！？
What?! What happened?!
クッソー！　やっぱり　まだムリか！
Damn it!
It still didn't work!
《チャクラの衣がなくなった。
やはりムリを…》
His cloak of chakra is gone.
He overdid it...
テマリ様！
敵が連合の中に突っ込んできて→
Lady Temari!
The enemy has broken through
our ranks! Many are hurt!
多くの負傷者が…。
（テマリ）みんな　負傷者の回収を急げ。
Everyone, hurry and gather the wounded!
医療チームへ回せ！
それから　みんなに→
Notify the Medical Team!
Tell all to maintain
a standby position at a distance—!
自分から近づかず
距離を保てと伝え…。
うわ～っ！
大丈夫か！？
しっかりしろ！
Are you all right?!
Hey, hang on!
ゴムのおっちゃん　今すぐ→
Hey, Bendy Guy!
ビーのおっちゃんと八尾に
話がしてえ。
I need to get a hold of Octopops
and Eight Tails right away!
なぁ　連絡って　どうすりゃいい？
How do I reach them?!
ここの連絡班を通して
情報部長の山中いのいちに→
Go through the Comm Corps and
have Intel Unit Captain Inoichi
Yamanaka connect you with Bee.
ビーたちと中継してもらえばいい。
連絡班を探せばいいんだな。
I just have to look for
a Comm Corps Shinobi, huh?
よかったな。
え？
You're in luck.
俺も連絡班の忍だ。
Huh?!
I'm with the Comm Corps.
おぉ！
All right!
ナルト　気をつけろ！
Naruto! Watch out!
《三本貫手を引いた…
パンチで気絶を狙う気だな！》
He's withdrawn
his Three-Fingered Assault!
He's aiming for a KO with a punch.
（ドダイ）熔遁　護謨玉！
Lava Style: Rubber Sphere!
《いのいち：あなたは
雲隠れのドダイ殿。　どうした！？
Lord Dodai of the Hidden Cloud!
What do you need?
ナルトが　ビーと八尾に話があるそうだ。
Naruto needs to speak to
Bee and Eight Tails.
今すぐ連絡を取れるように
してやってくれ。
Please contact them immediately!
三代目　雷影が
偽のゴムボールを追っているうちに》
While the Third Raikage is still chasing
after the dummy Rubber Ball!
《ゴムボールで
囲ったように見せかけて→
He made it look like
he had me inside that ball,
後ろから俺を引き抜いて
岩陰に隠す。
but he pulled me out and
hid me behind a boulder!
ゴムのおっちゃんも
早技だってばよ！》
Bendy Guy thinks fast!
ゴムのおっちゃん　ありがとう！
Thanks, Bendy Guy!
これで　ビーのおっちゃんと
会話の時間が取れた。
Now I'll have time to talk
to Octopops!
と言っても　すぐに気づかれる。
それほど時間の猶予はないと思え。
He'll probably catch on right away!
Remember, you don't have much time!
うん！
Yeah!
《ナルト…　ビー殿と八尾２人に
話があるそうだが→
Naruto, you want to talk
to Bee and Eight Tails,
近くにいないのか？　行動を
ともにしているはずだろ？》
but aren't they nearby?
You're supposed to
be working together.
《今は近くにいねえし　それに→
They're not here now. Besides...
って…　そんなことより
早く連絡をつけてくれってばよ！
Never mind, hurry and
contact them please!
時間がねえんだ！》
There's no time!
（八尾）ナルトは先に行っちまったぞ。
Naruto's gone on ahead!
さっさと用を済ませろ！
いつまでやってんだ！
Hurry up and finish your business!
How long is it going to take?!
（キラービー）尿意は己の意志とは相違。
The urge to go pee is
beyond one's control... y'see?
《ビーのおっちゃん　ナルトだってばよ。
Octopops, it's me, Naruto!
俺ってば　八尾に
直接聞きたいことがあるんだ。
I have to ask Eight Tails something!
早く　八尾と替わってくれ！》
Put him on!
今は生理現象。
話しかけられると　集中力　減少。
Relieving oneself takes concentration.
So let me focus on urination.
なんで　こんなときに　交渉。
I can't talk now...
替わったぞ　ナルト。
どうした？　慌ててるようだが。
I'm here, Naruto! What's going on?
You seem to be in a panic!
《八尾は　三代目雷影と→
Hey, Eight Tails...
You've fought the Third Raikage
before, right?
やりあったことが
あるんだよな？》
あぁ　ずっと昔にな。
Yeah, long ago.
打たれ強く
頑丈な人間だったぞ　ありゃ。
He was solid and
could take the blows.
一本貫手って技で
尾を８本全部→
Once, he used this move called
the One-Fingered Assault
切られちまったことも
あるくらいだ。
and cut off all my tails.
《どうやって　じいちゃん雷影の
胸に傷を負わせたんだ？》
How did you manage to scar
Gramps Raikage on the chest?
え？　俺の
尾獣玉じゃなかったかな？
Huh?!
Maybe it was my Tailed Beast Bomb?
いや　どうだったかな…。
No, maybe it wasn't...
お互い　技を構えたまま力尽きて
前のめりに倒れてたからな。
We were pushing against
each other with all our might,
and we both fell forward.
あんまりよく覚えてねえな。
I don't quite remember.
《もしかして…》
Maybe...
《ありがとだってばよ　八尾》
Hey thanks, Eight Tails!
影分身の術！
Shadow Clone Jutsu!
《なんだ？
さっきのとは違うのか！？》
What? Is this different
from the one earlier?!
じいちゃん雷影が
ここに突っ込んできてる。
Gramps Raikage is headed this way.
ゴムのおっちゃんは　ひいててくれ。
やってみたいことがあるんだ。
When he gets here,
get out of the way, Bendy Guy!
There's something I want to try.
わかった。
Got it.
螺旋丸！
Rasengan!
みんな！　今は手出しするな！
Everyone! Do not assist!
封印班は準備しておけ！
はっ！
Sealing Corps! Stand by!
Right!
《何をする気か知らないが
そいつは　ただの螺旋丸だぞ。
I don't know
what he's planning,
but that's just a Rasengan!
それで　いけるのか！？》
Is that going to be enough?
《最強の矛で　ナルトの手足を
確実に　もいでいく。
His Invincible Spear will cut
through Naruto's arms and legs.
半殺しにして
連れて帰ることにするか》
I'll have him brought back
to me half-dead.
《仙人モードの蛙組手。
Sage Mode: Frog Kumite!
こっちのほうが
危険感知は広いし早い。
With this, I can sense danger
over a wider range, and it's faster!
だから　突きをギリギリでかわして…》
So I'll be able to counter
at the last minute...
《ちゃんと腕を狙える！》
And aim straight for his arm!
思ったとおりだってばよ！
Just like I thought!
《そうか…　あの胸の傷は
そういうことだったのか》
I see... That's how he got
that scar on his chest!
（２人）やった！
– We did it!
よっしゃ！　いいぞ　ナルト！
よし！
All right! Way to go, Naruto!
Yes!
よく気づいたな。
That was sharp of you!
八尾が三代目雷影と戦ったとき
技を構えたまま→
Eight Tails told me that they were
pushing as hard as they could,
前のめりに倒れたって
言ったから→
then fell forward.
そのときに
自分の技が胸に当たって→
I figured that he must've fallen
on his own hand.
それで　ついた傷だと思ったんだ。
自分でつけた傷だから
恥だってこと。
He injured himself.
That's why it was so embarrassing.
最強の盾と最強の矛を持つ忍。
He was the shinobi with
the ultimate spear and shield...
確かに矛盾している。
What a paradox.
三代目は　矛のほうが
強かったってことか。
Lord Third's spear was stronger,
it seems...
うん。
Yeah!
たぶん　忍最強の盾を
持ってるのは→
Probably the shinobi with
the greatest shield is Gaara!
我愛羅だってばよ。
（水影）お前が土影の名を
受け継ぐのは　わかってたがな。
I always knew you'd be Tsuchikage.
今じゃ無理がたたって→
But look at you now...
An old man riddled with back pain.
腰痛持ちのじじいに
成り下がってるじゃねえか。
腰の入った重いパンチに
変えたはいいが→
I'll admit that was a punch
with some power to it...
重すぎて　腰がガッタガタ…　って→
but you overdid it and
strained your back!
おい　早く逃げろ。
鬼灯一族の水鉄砲の術だ。
Anyway! Hurry up and run!
I'm about to use
the Hozuki Clan's Water Gun Jutsu!
（我愛羅）ハァ　ハァ　ハァ…。
hitomi tojite kokyuu tomete kasanariae futatsu no kage yo
closing my eyes, holding my breath, overlap two shadows
hikare hikare hikare sayonara namida
shine, shine, shine, goodbye tears
hitomi tojite
closing my eyes...
naki yamu koto no nai sora aoku tsutsumu machi wo
we once stood side by side gazing at
itsuka futari de narande nagameteta
the tear-drenched sky that wrapped the city in blue
mimi wo sumaseba
if I listen carefully
ima mo kimi no koe ga kikoeru
I can still hear your voice
mouichido dake ano koro mitai ni
hold me once more
dakiyosete yo
just like that time
nee waratte kocchi muite namae yonde ichido dake de ii
please smile, look at me, call my name, just once more
hikare hikare hikare sayonara namida
shine, shine, shine, goodbye tears
toki wo tomete negai komete ai wo tomenaide konya dake wa
stop the time, I wish with all my heart, don't stop love, just for this night
maware maware maware sayonara memorii
turn around, turn around, turn around, goodbye memory
hitomi tojite
closing my eyes...
You were cooperative
until just now!
What happened? Have you decided
to side with the enemy?
I am a former Kage, after all.
I am helping you out...
Just in a different way.
皆様　お変わりございませんか？
Which is what exactly?
美空ひばりです。
If you can't win against me
using all of your abilities,
では　最後まで
ごゆっくり　お楽しみください。
that means you're less
than dead old me, you fool!
Next time on Naruto Shippuden:
"Terror: The Steam Imp"
『木曜８時のコンサート
名曲！　にっぽんの歌』。
How are you gonna win against
the enemy boss like that?!
２時間スペシャル！
今回は
ご覧の豪華な歌手の皆さん→